[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
hello everyone this is felina for
software engineering radio today with me
i have two guests firstly chris ricomini
is a software engineer startup investor
and advisor with more than a decade of
experience at major tech companies and
the author of apache samsa also with me
dmitry riaboy a software engineer and
engineering manager that's worked at a
variety of companies and helped create
apache parquet he's currently the vice
president of software engineering at the
mergen
together dmitri and chris wrote the book
the missing readme that is the topic of
today's episode so firstly a question
like what is this book about who is this
book for like of course it's called the
missing readme but the readme of what
first off thanks for having us on the
show it's it's great to join you this
morning at least morning for us
so the book is really for a few
different audiences
i think the impetus for writing the book
first off was
a few years ago i inherited a team of
engineers to manage and many of them
were pretty entry level and so i was
doing the normal round of kind of
one-on-ones getting to know everybody
and talking about what they're working
on and stuff and i found myself
repeating what i was saying quite a bit
and i sort of converged on the idea that
there should really be a manual for this
to help new software engineers get up
and running and off the ground and kind
of integrate it into the the flow of
working at a company as a professional
so i would say one of the audiences is
actually the managers that are hopefully
excited to hand out this book to the
people working for them help them kind
of bootstrap new hires and stuff our
aspiration and actually our intent that
you know we keep a stack of these under
our desks for for people as they on
board if they need to get going we can
we can help them out with it second and
main audience i would say is really
engineer sort of in the zero to five
year experience range either just coming
out of college just entering the
workforce
this cohort of engineers has
a lot of good
computer science fundamental experience
so they've been trained you know
operating systems and compilers and
programming languages and stuff like
that they tend to have a little bit
pitting with somewhat of a broad brush
here but this is has been my impression
they tend to have a little bit less
experience
doing sort of i wouldn't call it softer
skills but just knowing how a company
works and like how to interact with a
manager how to interact with other teams
even how to work with a team you know
oftentimes in in university you know you
might have some projects that you do
with some of your students but a lot of
your work is done in isolation and of
course when you join a company almost
all of your work is not done in
isolation
it can be a little bit disorienting so
that's i would say the second audience
and then the third audience is somewhat
similar but i think has sort of the
inverse skill set of a new college grad
and this is a boot camp type engineer so
people that have you know maybe
zero to however many years of real world
work experience but in perhaps a
different field so these you know we've
hired boot camps at we pay the company i
currently work for boot camp graduates
that have come from you know there were
lawyers we had somebody that we hired
that was an editor or like a book editor
they often have a fairly
broad skill set and also experience
interacting with managers working at
companies understanding how things work
in a little bit more detail than perhaps
your new college graduate might
but on the other hand they tend to have
a little bit less on the cs fundamental
side of things so whereas a new college
graduate has you know four years of
class after class after class of cs
fundamentals the bootcamper might have
like six months of intensive training
oftentimes in kind of a full stack
environment and they get trained up in
like one language or two languages and
then a stack of some sort whether that's
like node or python or something like
that and so the book kind of somewhat
ambitiously tries to cover all this but
it's it's not meant to cover it in super
deep detail and so what we do is we
cover sort of a lot of the technical
stuff that you wouldn't get taught in a
university setting so this is like some
of the details of modern testing how you
interact with legacy code and work on
refactoring stuff like that how you do
operations so like new college graduates
are not often taught how to be on call
and it turns out when you go into the
workforce oftentimes you go on call and
you get paged and you have to answer
questions and nobody really tells you
how to do this so there's like sort of a
technical portion of the book and then
there's a more process oriented portion
of the book that's about managers and
like promotions and even design
discussions stuff like that so it's
meant to address sort of both of these
audiences that's a great answer such a
diverse book that covers different
skills and of course me working at a
university sort of part of your audience
is coming from my pipeline so i very
much recognize this well you teach them
cs fundamentals there's so much more to
know it's exactly that there is just to
add to what chris was saying most of the
time the way people learn how to code
and the way they get into their first
software engineering job it's working on
their own project and they don't get
really get to see the work of
maintaining the code and working with
the team to keep it running right so you
get sort of this very nice clean sort of
maybe you have an exercise where there's
an existing piece of code you need to
modify it and that's great but then you
modify it and you're done you submit
your assignment you get your grade you
never look at it again whereas when
you're working on something you're just
looking at the thing all the time and
other people are looking at that thing
all the time and it's evolving under you
and it's a different mode of working and
a lot of the things that we spend time
on in the book are about
sort of the practices that have
developed within the industry for
dealing with that and you just don't
really get that experience either in
college or in boot camp and often you
don't know what you don't know and in
terms of the genesis of the book i had a
similar experience to chris by the way
like chris and i have never actually met
in real life
wow this is we've sort of known each
other on the internet for a decade or so
but the experience is really parallel
with each other new people join and
they know how to program do they have
this maybe they have experience from
other things but there are certain
things where they don't even know what
you're talking about when you start
talking about it and to somebody who's
been around for a while it's so second
nature we don't recognize it as a topic
to teach because it's not algorithmic
complexity you know or clever ways to
traverse a binary tree or whatever like
those things are obvious that like
there's a thing here you need to learn
it
how to do logging well
it's just logging right but actually
it's really complicated
yeah i think we will definitely get to
to logging and more practical skills but
firstly i want to
go back to one of the things you also
talk about that you were just hinting at
is the idea of technical debt right that
indeed in university or in a booth camp
you make an exercise and maybe you
change codes but definitely you will not
be given
10 year olds a million lines of 10 year
old c code so i think what i really
liked about your book is that you
described two different forms of
technical debt that to me were new
prudent and reckless so maybe you can
dive into a brief summary for people in
the audience that might not know at all
what technical that is but specifically
prudent and reckless and what do you
think that that distinction adds
prudent and reckless technical that this
is an idea we got from martin fowler who
has a really informative website
martinfowler.com he describes a matrix
of the kinds of debt you might take out
so it's your standard two by two so one
side you have deliberate versus
inadvertent and on the other you have
reckless and prudent and so you can have
any combination of those two right so
you might have something that's reckless
and deliberate so you're deliberately
being reckless or you might have
something that's reckless and
inadvertent
we get into it in the book but
essentially there is
you consciously make a decision
to take on some debt and you have a plan
for how to address it or you consciously
make the decision that this is a risk
we're willing to take as you kind of
evaluate it and then there is
inadvertent when you don't know what you
don't know and maybe you do it because
so reckless and inadvertent is i don't
know what's going to happen but we're
just going to go and you just write some
stuff and you throw it out there and
then you have problems or you have
prudent inadvertent where you know
there's an unknown and you know you need
to move forward and you say here's how
we're gonna
monitor this to learn more and when we
learn more inevitably we're going to do
something about it and the fact is
especially that kind of that is
unavoidable if you're going to make any
forward progress right as we start
building a program as it starts being
used by real humans you find out more
about the problem and then you learn how
maybe you should have solved it right
and then now you have technical debt but
you couldn't have addressed it before
you started writing and in fact the
definition of technical that that kind
of the original definition where the
term came from is about that about
learning the original term came about
from trying to explain to sort of
non-technical people that sometimes we
gotta
write the thing and it's not gonna be
quite right because through the process
of creating software to solve this
problem we're gonna learn more about the
problem and we're going to understand it
better and that's why we always need to
revise right that's why it's not right
once and it's done it's usually write it
improve it keep improving it it keeps
living and changing because yeah i think
this is such a useful distinction
especially indeed for people that are
new that don't really understand how to
do something and then you want to
communicate like sometimes it's okay if
you don't understand how to do something
but sometimes you can make some
predictions
one of the things you advise in the book
sort of against technical debt to pay
off technical debt so to say is to do
minor refactorings like make small fixes
so i was wondering like where does that
advice come from because i can imagine
that making small fixes can also be like
oh a bit of duct tape here oh a tie wrap
there and then you know you build this
bigger monster isn't that sort of
conflicting with creating more reckless
technical deaths how do you see that
in practical experience addressing
technical debt takes a lot of different
strategies so
it really is dependent on the kind of
technical that you're dealing with and
if you know
what to do about it right so there are
certainly some cases where it's
appropriate to do large-scale like
refactoring efforts those are really
complicated and really hard to get right
i have seen them done correctly but
it usually requires the entire
organization like grinding to a halt
before there's an appetite to do that so
oftentimes you find yourself having to
do things incrementally whether it is an
ideal state or not
in some cases it is an ideal state so i
think when you're doing a smaller
refactoring there's kind of two kinds of
debt that you can address with that mode
one is like
minor cleanup kind of stuff where it's
not a systemic problem that you're
dealing with but it's something that's
limited and maybe more isolated so maybe
there's some utility class that needs to
get refactored and everyone knows it
needs to get refactored you're you know
mucking around with it you might decide
that this is something that i'm going to
take on it's fairly fairly minor i can
do it in you know a day or two and i
think as long as that's handled
appropriately and then the commits are
separated so it's not intermingled with
your regular feature work you can be
pretty successful with that the second
kind of technical debt approach is where
you actually know the long term like
what the end state that you want to get
to and you can march toward it
incrementally that's like the ideal
right and so for example with my own
teams we will
sort of have an escalating approach to
technical debt where on the first chunk
we have sort of the minor stuff that we
do
as we're working and usually we'll
budget a bit of time to do some of that
work
but the second step up from that is like
there's a project that's like maybe a
quarter that we can budget in and the
third one is sort of like that very
large chunk of work yeah and in addition
to what chris just said the reason we
make a point of talking about minor
refactoring is that it's very easy to
get into these dichotomies of people
saying just don't touch it and
you know unless you're really really
ready to tackle it leave it alone or
you know you just gotta burn it down and
start all over like let's re-architect
the whole thing we're gonna switch
languages there's a new framework on
hacker news so let's adopt that you can
make things better by just fixing them
as you go along like while you're in
there you see that you know the api the
some internal api is not quite right or
there's inconsistency in how certain
libraries are used or something needs to
be upgraded just go ahead and do it you
know it doesn't need to be a giant big
deal where
you know it's prioritized by the all the
managers and there's a committee that
decides when to do refactoring like you
see something that's a little broken you
can just fix it it's okay
especially when you're inheriting the
million lines of c code type thing where
it'll just take a while
the little things do add up right as
long as there's like chris was saying as
long as there's agreement about where
you need to take things and you're not
just changing so that now there's 17
different coding styles in the same code
base you don't need to stop the world
and sort of redo the whole thing right
like you can do it a chunk at a time as
you go along
yeah i think that's really good advice
because indeed if you wait for this
perfect opportunity in which there will
be no feature requests for three months
that clearly is never gonna happen right
so i totally understand you need to do
this step by step so you actually in the
book you describe sort of an algorithm
so to say to deal with legacy codes
maybe you can
summarize that and explain the
background of that too sure this also
isn't something that we came up with
most of the ideas in the book are
borrowed so this is the the legacy code
change algorithm from
michael feathers who wrote a book called
working effectively with legacy code i
guess it's a little bit dated now it
came out in 2004 but it's it's quite
good and the algorithm as he proposed is
to identify change points find
test points break dependencies write
tests and then make changes and refactor
and we walk through each of those steps
and explain what michael feathers means
by those although of course to get the
full treatment you should just read the
book this is our general approach to all
these topics we'll tell you what the
general idea is so you know there's a
there there and it's a thing and people
talk about it and there's materials and
then we give you references for books or
other resources to to really get deep on
it alternatively of course if instead of
reading the book you could also listen
to software engineering episodes
295 in which i actually interviewed
michael feathers about this book so that
might be like this little step between
fantastic yeah then our episode that
really dives into legacy codes in a
whole episode and then maybe read the
book and with that maybe we can also
like move on to the next topic because
indeed your book you know covers a few
of these topics add a little bit of
a broad view to weave it all together
something else that your book talks
about which i really thought was very
valuable as a concept is defensible
programming what is defensible program
so this is i think a term that's been
around for a while
and people do it often times sort of
intuitively but they're essentially a
set of practices you can use to kind of
both protect yourself as the author from
having to deal with bugs later on and
also to protect the software from
unexpected behavior so
there's a whole set of practices around
null pointers for example and input
validation so especially in untyped
languages
you know you get a parameter passed in
and you really have no clue what's in
that parameter that you can assume it's
the string you always hoped it would be
or you can expect it to be you know
anything there's a whole set of these
practices to protect everybody that's
involved with the code and also to
handle failures in a more graceful way
one thing we do in the book is we have
these sidebars of sharing our personal
experiences or experiences we're very
close to that illustrate these points
and like how this stuff comes about so
if you don't mind i'll share the one
that we have about defensive programming
where i made a big goof that as far as i
know is still out there affecting people
my first job i might have been still in
my undergraduate at the time but it was
working in this genomic analysis service
this was back when the human genome
project was just well it was fully
underway but it hadn't finished yet so
this is like around the year 2000 early
2000s and we provided uh online service
for scientists to upload dna sequences
and do something with them search for
stuff at the time the way that a lot of
scientists a lot of biologists thought
about dna as strings they just needed a
place to type it right so often we
expected a text file right the text file
there's a standard format for how you
represent dna you know all the ac's tngs
and we explain what the format is but
then of course scientists would go and
like type it straight up into word and
upload a doc file a word document file
my crappy little parser didn't parse
that because it expected a text file and
so of course internally through an error
it tried to read the thing and it didn't
work and what resulted for the user was
no results are found we didn't tell them
that there was a problem processing
their input we told them there are no
results right and so they would
then contact some of them would contact
us and say why were there no results
there definitely should be and some of
them would just go away thinking there
are no results and like that goes into
their scientific research right so it's
rather terrible and of course my
terrible solution to this problem was to
put a big icon on the submission form
that had a word crossed out with the red
line and that drove down the number of
those errors and so everybody was happy
and you know i got a boy from from my
manager for solving in this way but
that's not defensible programming right
like this is avoiding the problem this
is i didn't write a parser for word i
didn't
throw an error upon receiving this thing
to say don't submit it this way please
submit it a different way so there is
nothing there fundamentally that
prevented there it was just sort of
trying to get the user to not do the
stupid thing or annoy that they were
doing you know it was the classic blame
the user thing
but the visual treatment worked until
they redesigned the website i'd left the
job and literally while writing this
book i went to check the website it's
still around the tool is still up
they changed the ui and that little icon
is not there
so on a lark i decided to type some dna
into into a doc file and i submitted it
and sure enough it went clean through
and i got zero results so it's still
returning bad
15 years later removed 20 years later
it's still
you know giving scientists bad results
because i was too lazy to deal with bad
input wow that's a great story so this
is an example of what is not defensible
programming so so maybe you also have
and why it matters but i'm wondering if
you also have a good example of like a
pro example of what is defensible
programming in this case the answer
would have been
expect that you will have all kinds of
wild inputs from your users be it you
know people upload their own kind of
file or the data doesn't match and be
clear about your expectations and either
you know ideally of course you treat
everything and you're able to process
everything but
silent failure is is really the the
error here right like if you're gonna
fail fail early and tell people like
what the problem is so that they can
address it this comes up in a wide
variety of places user input is the
classic one but also you know services
change their apis and things start
timing out and how are you gonna deal
with that what you don't want is a
failure and a giant stacked trace that's
facing the user right you want to sort
of
think about your your failure conditions
and how to defend against them because
they are going to happen
especially as we start working on web
skill stuff this is maybe the graceful
failing that chris was mentioning right
yeah like know that it's going to happen
it
won't be the ideal flow all the time
yeah something else you mentioned in the
category of defensible programming is
avoiding null values so
how and and maybe also why like how can
i not use no values i have to initialize
something like like how does that work
can you maybe give some practical
examples of why that matters and how to
go about it
yeah
noel is definitely one of those hot
topics especially these days is among a
lot of more the functional programmers
among us but one of the classic patterns
that we see increasingly popular over
the past decade or so is using like
optionals instead of null and so the
idea there is that you're not or rarely
dealing with an actual null value what
you're dealing with is a structure that
is called an optional and it can be
either something or it can be nothing
because of the fact that you are dealing
with an actual object and you need to
either pattern match or extract the
value from it it forces you through the
api to think through both the there's
something here path and also the there's
something not here path and to deal with
the something not your path explicitly
so that's i think a very common one so
maybe diving into that in more
mainstream languages because it's clear
how that would work in haskell or
f-sharp these pure functional languages
but now in in java or in c if i want to
have an optional or maybe how do i do
that practically do i use a library do i
write myself do i just use this way of
thinking in a data type it's not that
complex you can write it yourself there
are also
libraries the way things evolve probably
between us talking now and the episode
coming out there might be a new one
there's quite a few i first encountered
this line of thinking through scala but
java has since adopted that
superficially at first it seems like
it's not really different from now right
you can check if the thing is now do
something or you can say
if the option contains something do
something right like what's the
difference i can still always get my
null point intercept from by calling a
get on the option at the wrong time the
major difference there is that
null
will
throw kind of run time exceptions if you
dereference it wrong whereas the option
mode that really allows you to deal with
the thing within the kind of regular
flow versus the exceptional flow so you
mean if it's not at run time what you
mean is that it will then fail at
compile time if you don't handle it
properly right
i'm thinking of ways that you can still
force it to fail at runtime because you
can still wind up doing something with
where you're the reference to now if you
really try hard in general
yes if you are properly there's a big
caveat but if you're properly using you
know optionals you should essentially
get compile time warnings or errors
another language i was just dealing with
recently is swift and they essentially
have something like an optional with
lets and you can do an exclamation mark
or whatever it is to get the actual
value out and what i found myself doing
this is for a side project and i was
just hacking around but this is like
definitely not the right way to do
things is i would just essentially call
get on everything and ignore the other
path the nun path which is essentially
the same thing as just pretending that
it's a regular object and ignoring the
fact that it could be nil and so if you
abuse optionals or ignore their intent
then certainly you can get run time
errors but if you play by the rules and
are diligent about it you should for the
most part be in much better shape
and
as with everything and there's a big
caveat in our book like almost
everything is great there's almost no
absolutes in computer science so it's
hard to say for sure you're always going
to be safe if you use optionals right
and in fact there's a line of thinking
with java for instance where they push
you to only use optionals in certain
situations so all this stuff has a lot
of caveats around it but anyway
at a minimum if you're abusing it and
you understand what options are for it
does give you a little pang of shame
every time that you cheat
which is the feeling i felt as i was
playing around with swift so you're at
least somewhat aware that you're
breaking the rules a bit yeah this is
extra level of defense right so let's do
one more from the defensible programming
because i thought that was such an
interesting line of reasoning also as
you said in the beginning this is the
type of stuff that you don't learn in
school like literally so you also say
retry smart what is smart retrying this
is just an infinite loop of waiting for
three seconds and doing the api call
again maybe that's not smart what is
smart retrying
anytime something goes wrong you either
have an option of giving up and failing
or retrying or going through some
alternate code path right
and oftentimes especially when you're
dealing with network the answer is like
hey let's let's retry again at least a
few times right the most naive approach
is you just simply take the call you
made and call it again and there are
a number of issues with that approach so
you can essentially dos a service by if
there is a failure amongst a wide number
of services for example imagine a
machine
that is receiving calls sort of at a
steady rate and then it has a hiccup
maybe a garbage collection or something
and it's it's offline for a second so
now you've accrued a second's worth of
rpc calls amongst all of the upstream
services that are going to call it so
when it comes back online if they all
are just immediately retrying then you
now get this wave of rpc calls all
coming to this service and then of
course gc's again because now there's a
ton more halls than it expected and so
you get this kind of cascading effect
one of the things we talk about in the
book is like telescoping back off or
exponential back off or even just a
random sleep where when you retry you
don't just immediately retry but you
pause for a little bit of time and maybe
introduce something called jitter which
is like essentially a random weight or a
bounded random weight where you say you
know yeah i'm gonna wait two plus or
minus 500 milliseconds uh something like
that that is two seconds plus or minus
500 milliseconds and then maybe you tell
us go back so it's you know maybe it
starts at 50 milliseconds then 100 and
then 200 then 400 you're not banging
away on things something else that we
talk about in this area is item potency
if the rpc call you're making is
incrementing a counter for example and
you are retrying your call that is not
an item potent operation so if the call
was successful but the network timed out
you don't really know that the counter
was incremented so if you just naively
retry you are now double counting or
triple counting or quadruple counting
you might need some kind of item potent
operation and for that you could use
something like a id incremental id or
uid to allow the server to essentially
deduplicate the calls that you're making
so this is all network focused and this
is all sort of retry focused the retry
stuff i think applies writ large within
your own applications when you're
dealing with disks you know essentially
anything that's not in your nice little
cocoon of immediate code
yeah and of course this is where we do
get into a fairly active area of
computer science research proper
computer science research on distributed
systems and there's things like crgts
and all kinds of other things it is the
case that for like undergrads or boot
camp graduates they often don't see that
stuff and they kind of run into it much
earlier these days when everything is is
a service and you're talking to all
kinds of things online people who
haven't taken the graduate course on
distributed systems will end up building
distributed systems without realizing
that they're doing that and ideally they
would go full-on and learn the
distributed systems course material but
as is at least knowing that networks
fail you should expect that the network
will fail it will not just stay up you
should retry you shouldn't retry forever
you know how to do it in a nice way
right there's some basics that we just
want to make sure everybody generally
knows and then for the more advanced
concepts of course there's a whole
wealth of material there i just want to
plug you know a co-worker of mine wrote
a book that's pretty widely known as
sort of becoming canonical at this point
the designing data intensive
applications from martin klepman is sort
of like the reference book for a lot of
the distributed system data intensive
stuff so i highly recommend that book if
as a listener you're into this subject
or for that matter building
microservices or actually dealing with
stuff on a daily basis there's just so
much there
yeah that's a great tip we will
definitely put a link to martin's book
in the show notes let's move on to a
different topic then something else that
your book talks about is testing
specifically you distinguish different
types of testing the different uses of
testing i should say so what are
different ways in which testing is used
in a project
yeah so there's all kinds of ways that
you can test there are methodologies
where you write tests in order to
validate your own code as you go along
and encourage some best practices
there's unit testing which is sort of
validate that your logic is correct
there's integration testing validate the
various components of your system work
well together there's acceptance testing
which is sort of more about contracts
right like if a third party says give me
software that does x y and z then
acceptance testing is them
checking x y and z and signing off that
you delivered the thing you said that
you will deliver there's a variety of
different tests one common mistake is
all the tests go into one bucket and
then you wind up administration where
tests that you need to validate that the
small changes you're making aren't
breaking things you know should be
really fast but if you're running really
complex integration tests that you need
to run before you ship a version to
production they tend to be slow and they
tend to require a lot of setup so you
kind of slow down your whole development
cycle and it's a very easy trap to fall
into so we talk a little bit about that
sort of thing and different kinds of
tests there are lots of different
philosophies in testing there are some
people who say actually don't bother
with unit tests just write the
integration test because that's what the
user sees there are some people who
really advocate you know covering
everything with tests we suggest that
it's easy to go a little bit overboard
with that and to test the wrong thing
it's a very deep topic what they write
this isn't sometimes controversial this
is probably the single chapter that we
get the most feedback about where they
say that we got it wrong yeah i can
imagine there's quite a few different
philosophies and we're actually believe
it or not we're fairly aware of them and
we kind of had to choose one that seemed
to be reasonable for a beginner one of
the things as we were writing this
chapter that we we went through is
we thought it would be great to provide
some examples here's unit tests and
here's integration tests in the wild and
so we went out and we looked at a bunch
of open source projects some of which we
work on and
of course what you discover in the real
world is that
you know one person's unit test is
another person's integration test and
some people have you know integrations
tests that are actually acceptance tests
and so i think one of the things we
highlight in this chapter is like you
got to be a little bit pragmatic and
flexible about like when to use these
things what they're called don't be too
dogmatic about it the most important
thing is like you're testing your code
and validity and things are working and
so you know very frequently you'll find
integration tests that run as part of
the unit test suite that might or might
not be okay depending on the situation
it's just a very messy
area in terms of just the naming
hierarchy and when things get
implemented and where they line up the
thing we wanted to highlight for the new
software engineers like it's common that
things are messy and like it doesn't
mean you're a bad software engineer if
you're doing things in a slightly messy
way it also doesn't mean other people
are a bad software engineer if you know
you're looking at you know for i think
one of the projects i won't name the
project but we looked at it they had all
their integration tests kicking off
locally and they were like doing remote
calls to cloud services and stuff and so
just to run the unit test we'd involve
like installing service accounts for
various cloud providers and stuff and
that that's a little bit on the not
great side of things like i said you
have to be somewhat pragmatic about
dealing with this stuff one of the
points that we make about this
observation is that
and these software projects are very
impactful very useful have affected
thousands of engineers in a good way
made a lot of people much more
productive so let's not be too dogmatic
about these things when you see
something like that that doesn't mean oh
my god this is terrible it means oh my
god this has actually been a
collaboration between many different
people with a lot of different
backgrounds it's been evolving that said
if it's slowing you down and if it's
creating problems fix it yeah actually i
was going to say this is actually i
think good advice because you are right
as in many areas of software development
but specifically maybe in testing you do
have these different camps and there's
just like no way to get it right so i do
think especially for junior developers
it's great to hear sort of the voice of
the middle that yeah it's fine if one of
your unit tests is actually also an
integration test then it's not like you
know you're done as a professional this
this sometimes happens so
i i do think that that makes sense as an
advice specifically at that level
yet another topic on the book the book
really is a rich collection of all these
topics that matter for professionals
something that you also talk about is
code reviews specifically you coined
this idea that for me was new of doing a
walkthrough with the code review so what
is a code review walkthrough the general
idea here is a lot of the time these
days when people do code reviews it's
make a change put it up on
github gitlab whatever your tool is and
then somebody else looks at it so it's
asynchronous and we give a bunch of tips
for how to do this well in a way that
you critique the code and you don't
critique the people so it doesn't feel
personal it doesn't feel like an attack
how to write feedback how to process it
etc but it's also the case that
sometimes the change is big enough that
sort of a little blurb that says i'm
fixing a thing isn't sufficient to
really get people to understand it a lot
of the time this is i guess just how
humans are right you put up a 20 line
code change and you get five comments
you put up a 20 000 line code change
with all kinds of things in there you
just get a ship it they couldn't like
you can't process that so for larger
changes sometimes when you're doing
really structural stuff or is just
fairly intricate we do recommend that
you just grab time with a colleague and
walk them through what you're doing you
say here's what i'm doing over here
here's why i needed to modify that that
library and here's you know a different
way of thinking about you just really
give them rich context about what you're
doing and why and then they have the
appropriate context to give you feedback
on the code change the other thing i
would add is oftentimes we'll get like a
gotcha of like ah well you're just not
supposed to chip large pull requests
like anything over you know some number
of lines is is a no-no and so if you
break it up you'll never need a
walk-through or an in-person discussion
or even a virtual discussion and i think
there's different kinds of large so
there's large in terms of number of
lines of changes but there's also large
in terms of like mental capacity to
understand the complexity of what's
going on so for example you might have a
very i'll give you a real world example
we were refactoring a system at my
company which deals with money and so
this system is our ledger it's
responsible for tracking it's a source
of truth for the money movement at the
company so it's kind of a big deal and
we were editing some of the logic in a
state machine that was controlling it
was essentially a coordinator amongst a
number of machines that that were
tracking payments and so this is like a
very sophisticated piece of logic the
code is only 500 lines long or so and
it's like this this loop that's doing a
bunch of stuff based on events the
change itself you know might be 40 50
lines of code but
getting it right and understanding all
the edge cases and what's going on in
addition to the testing and stuff the
whole team needs to know
about this change and it really needs to
get explored in detail and discussed and
really analyzed and thought through and
so
setting up a walkthrough for a change
like that is hugely beneficial versus
you know blasting out the pull request
providing a design dock and sort of
walking away and waiting for comments a
lot of stuff you know especially remote
now it's important to have real
conversations where you can trigger some
of these thoughts that might not happen
in isolation yeah i want to go dive a
bit deeper into that topic because this
doesn't really seem to fit the github
flow so there is a pull request and then
comments happen asynchronously which is
also nice if you work in different time
zones so how do i do this do i plan
something like this or is this something
it's you're discussing all the pool
requests at one point someone says hey
maybe we need a walkthrough or do you
have like guidelines if there's more
than 100 lines so maybe we should how do
i fit i love this idea how do i fit this
into my project
i think both things happen so sometimes
if the asynchronous discussion on the
pull request gets maybe a little like
harmonious or two people are just
not understanding each other or it's
sort of well you can do it my way or you
do it your way i don't really care like
that kind of conversation starts
happening maybe that's the time to
actually have a little face to face
virtually or physically conversation
that resolves these things much more
generally advocably and quickly it's
easy to lose tone and to not understand
where people are coming from when you're
just exchanging the text messages so
that's one when sort of things feel like
they're starting to go south
just take a pause
find the time to sync up in person and
then the other is when you know that
there is this kind of rich context that
everybody needs to understand either
because the change is sophisticated not
necessarily large but maybe even subtle
and there's subtleties there that upon
just reading the code somebody might not
get and you need them to know this is
probably not something that somebody
fresh out of college should be doing
just that kind of change but if you
think there's something going on right
like tell people when you know you're
doing something that maybe is what i'm
actually doing is setting up for seven
more pull requests that are also going
to be small changes but let me tell you
where i'm going and let's sync up then
you do it pre-emptively different teams
have different processes around that
maybe there's a standing sort of design
discussion meeting or maybe you do it ad
hoc i just wanted to jump in on the open
source side of things it's one of those
things where i think you'll find a lot
of people are are definitely willing to
take time and have in-person chats but
it's not something that is i think
really part of the culture right now in
a lot of ways but i have definitely had
in-person chats on a number of different
open source projects airflow chatting
with with people amundsen or amazon
rather data catalog that we use and so
oftentimes if you ask hey can we hop on
a zoom or hop on a google video chat you
know modular time zones it's a great way
to
discuss the change but also build sort
of relationships with the community in
some ways i would just encourage people
to try it you get a lot more engagement
than you expect and that it is also
quite useful so i totally buy the it is
not part of the culture not part of the
git flow github pull request cycle you
know writ large i think some of the more
mature
projects when i say mature i mean in
terms of like process so projects that
are under apache or cncf like that um
and have multiple companies working with
them they're they're i think more apt
and more likely to
have
you know community meetings meetups
weekly sync up stuff like that in those
cases it's a little more common but you
know your average like ruby gem on
github that's maintained by you know
maybe a college student or somebody then
that's far less likely but i don't think
that's because they're unwilling to do
it it's just something that i think has
it really sort of happened as a like
mainstream thing but it's it's really
beneficial and it does it does work
awesome to close that topic if you do
want to know more about coach reviews we
had a show on that as well show number
400 with dr mckayla kreiler goes into
code reviews a lot deeper but this book
has so much more to offer us that we
could talk about one of the things this
came up very early in this episode
already is logging
so logging is something that maybe you
don't learn in school can you give some
ideas of what are practical best
practices that your book covers
i've spent the unbelievable
chunk of my life dealing with vlogging
being served in the data field which is
not something i would have predicted
coming out of undergrad there's a couple
of things one i don't want to over
generalize but
frequently when
folks do their programming outside of
kind of a professional environment
logging is just
writing some stuff to standard out or
maybe the subfile right it's
print line i got to this point and i'm
doing the next thing
and that's completely sufficient and and
fine and then you get into
industry and you realize people are
using logging libraries that have
logging levels and you need to
understand what those levels are and
it's just one of those things that is
pretty fast to learn but nobody bothers
to teach you we bother to write it down
so that you can read about it what are
these log levels mean i mean of course
it's documented right they can look it
up on the web but you need to know to
look it up what do these log levels mean
what to put and where
a little bit of kind of philosophy on
you know what is a warning and what is
info and what's the difference in a
warning and an error and the fatal that
sort of thing so maybe we can dive into
those topics a little bit more so so
what are different log levels for people
in the audience that might not be
familiar with that see that's where i
need to pull out the book and check
that's okay let's see i'll take a crack
at it
fatal error worn info debug trace i
believe that is the worst to best level
and when i say that every
framework and or language has its own
verbage so some of them you know might
get a little fuzzy there and some not
all of them have fatal and not all of
them have error that's generally what
you'll find is that sequence i believe i
would just say we also in addition to
the levels we talked quite a bit about
sort of best practices so how to keep
your logs fast where logs go like are
they going to disc are they going remote
you know redaction and not logging
passwords email you know pii which is
personally identifiable information like
emails and usernames and stuff there's a
lot that goes into good production grade
logging that is not obvious even from
the error api that you're calling like
one of the most common things you'll see
is like someone will call the log info
and they'll have their string that
they're logging and then they'll
concatenate a
dynamic value to that string like
starting server with port and then you
know plus and then the port number right
and string concatenation is a slow
operation and if you are not logging at
the info level you are burning cpu on
something that that is is not useful and
so there's like all kinds of practices
and little tricks that are not obvious
that by tweaking the way that you're
logging things you can really get a lot
more performance out of your application
you know i've been in many situations
where i've done performance analysis and
in the tight loop the trace log line
that is just never being read by anyone
is taking up like 80 of the cpu cycle so
there's like a lot of gotchas that are
just not obvious with logging at all i
used to joke that eventually my
retirement gig would be a string
concatenation consultant where i would
just go to people's code bases and fix
how they use strings and make their code
run for 10 faster
because there's so much of that out
there and you can basically do it with a
shell script right just like fix
people's stuff one practical tip
printing stack traces they're usually
multi-line and once you go into uh kind
of industrial deployments there are
usually systems that suck up all the
logging that different services do and
make them available for search etc but
they tend to work on a line by line
basis so if your message isn't contained
within a single line it gets broken up
and good luck reconstructing back your
27 line stack trace that has been sort
of broken up into 27 separate messages
and mixed together with similar logs
from all the other deployments of the
same service and now they're all kind of
shuffled together right so there are
plenty of ways to deal with that
structured logging you know there are
loggers that will log things in json
format for you and capture these sorts
of things it's a little bit of work
initially but then it just saves you a
ton of time if you're using one of these
like elk stack type log processors
nice yeah those are really nice
practical tips and advice for logging
which is indeed a topic that you would
think in theory it's fixed but in
practice it can lead to so many issues
we're nearing the end of the episode is
there like one topic that you really
like about the book where you're like oh
i have this nugget of advice that i
really want to share before we wrap it
up the section we have on handling
dependencies and understanding versions
it is really not something people talk
about enough and it's one of the biggest
time sinks and sources of unexpected
problems that i see people run into and
not just juniors right it's really
important to understand the dependencies
that you're introducing what those
libraries are what the versions mean
that you depend on and what will happen
when versions change
whether or not they will change in you
without you knowing it because of the
way you've instrumented the dependencies
what's
1.2.7 going to 1.2.8 means versus 1.2.7
going to 2.1.2 means so like sort of the
major minor type versions and what to
expect from that stuff so what do you
have some practical tips there so
knowing what version numbers means
that's definitely a tip but there aren't
any practical advice or maybe a nice
anecdote to have about dependencies that
people can learn from i think chris has
an idea here
again there's no 100 percent guidance
but pin your version numbers so that
things do not change underneath you is
something that i am fairly dogmatic
about and there are there are definitely
competing philosophies and people that
you think you should you know pin major
and minor but not not the patch version
or people think that you should always
pull on the latest stuff but i've just
dealt with so many problems that stem
from like we're pulling in some open
source project and either it we have not
pinned and by pinning i mean setting an
explicit version number on your
dependency such that you will always use
that version versus an unpin version
number where you might you essentially
leave it to the build or the build
system to pick what the right version
number is and in cases where there is a
new version available it will pull that
version in for you that behavior leads
to all kinds of exciting stuff during ci
and build time where things that worked
and have not changed suddenly stop
working for a variety of reasons that
class of problems is so maddening to
deal with and it saps energy and it's
just it ruins the fidelity of your tests
and it's such an insidious problem i
have experienced this type of thing
myself and it is indeed it is so
terrible because you have this this
commits and you're like okay before this
commit it works and after this commit it
fails so i'm going to read this a
hundred times right because this is the
offender and it's not the offender
someone else that i have no control over
as soon as you decided to remove a
feature i was depending on even worse
you decided okay i'm going to revert
this commit and you revert it and it
still doesn't work that same checksum
used to work
i think this is really good practical
advice this is like the stuff from the
trenches so to say right that you don't
teach this in schools or in universities
you would say you have to learn this by
doing it but of course it's way more
efficient than experts senior people
like you share this advice and put it in
a book one other thing i would i wanted
to throw out there i think in line with
your question about
if people walked away with one thing
that we could upvote into their brain
what would it be it's compatibility and
this is kind of adjacent to the
dependencies but under really
understanding forwards and backwards
compatibility and what these different
names mean i think
whether you're dealing with data or apis
whether that's a library api or a
microservice api that's remote
understanding what it means when you add
like a required field or when you delete
a required field or when you change a
data type from you know inch to long or
inch to string like what that is going
to do to the upstream and downstream
dependencies of you in a professional
environment it's so important to
understand that you're working within a
team and you're going to affect other
people's code and it's not something
that is at all obvious like it seems so
benign to just add like oh i need a
field in my database or i need a field
in my api i'm going to set it to
required and then that simple change can
bring down the whole the whole website
the whole microservice the whole
application can crash so i would say
understanding compatibility is
definitely something we cover that i
think in the the evolvability chapter we
talk about that in some detail so that
would be my
pet
guidance almost circles back to
dimitri's example of the word button
right that if you make something it is
not always clear how it's going to be
used the interface around my change so
then you in the software you still need
to be prepared against anything because
you can't depend on other people you and
you don't know like what you depend on
and who might depend on you if you're
building a library or framework so
have you ever really been happy with
your project management tool most are
too simple for a growing engineering
team to manage everything or too complex
for anyone to want to use them without
constant product shortcut formerly known
as clubhouse is different though because
it's worse wait no we mean it's better
shortcut is project management built
specifically for software teams it's
fast intuitive flexible powerful and
many other nice positive adjectives
let's look at some highlights team-based
workflows individual teams can use
shortcuts default workflows or customize
them to match the way they work org-wide
goals and roadmaps the work in these
workflows is automatically tied into
larger company goals it takes one click
to move from a roadmap to a team's work
to individual updates and vice versa
type vcs integrations whether you use
github gitlab or bitbucket shortcut ties
directly to them so you can update
progress from the command line the rest
of shortcut is just as keyboard friendly
with their power bar allowing you to do
virtually anything without touching your
mouse throw that thing in the trash
iterations planning set weekly
priorities and then let shortcut run the
schedule for you with accompanying
burndown charts and other reporting give
it a try at shortcut.com se radio again
that's shortcut.com
se radio shortcut again formerly known
as clubhouse because you shouldn't have
to project manage your project
management
[Music]
where can we read more about your work
like where can we find the book we will
make sure that we put everything in the
show notes but i just want to give you
an opportunity to shout out to your
website or your twitter or whatever you
want us to link to in the show
yeah so the missingreadme.com is the
website for the book where you can look
at it a little bit more and of course
it's available on amazon and everywhere
else where books are sold if people read
it would love reviews would love to find
out what folks think about it as you of
course know reviews are very important
for the authors to have to report the
book out there in the world to hear back
i am on twitter at square cog yeah i'm
on twitter at uh see rikomini so cnn my
last name the website has that
controversial chapter the text chapter
is available for free so if you go to
the missingreadme.com you can download
that pdf and come after us on twitter
now that we've given you our twitter
handles
nice awesome so we'll make sure to add
those links to the show notes thanks
again for writing this wonderful book
and thanks for being on the show today
with me
thanks for having us
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening
[Music]